Register of the David Harris Papers, 1926-1988.
Hoover Institution Archives
David Harris papers
1926-1988
67000
Harris, David, 1900-
8 manuscript boxes, 15 card file boxes, 6 envelopes, 8 medals (11.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, research notes, newsletters, lists, and printed matter, relating to Emperor Napoleon I of France, the Balkan crisis of 1875-1878, international affairs in Europe during the interwar period, and reconstruction of Germany and Austria following World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1967.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Napoleon I, Emperor of the French, 1769-1821.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Austria.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Peace.; World War, 1939-1945--Territorial questions--Germany.; Austria.; Balkan Peninsula.; Europe.; Europe--History--1918-1945.; France.; Germany.; Germany--History--20th century.; Rhineland (Germany)--History--Separatist movement, 1918-1924.
Biographical Note
1900 Born, Texas
1930-1938 Assistant Professor of History, Stanford University
1938-1942 Associate Professor of History, Stanford University
1942-1947 Associate Chief, Central European Affairs, U.S. Department of State
1947-1966 Professor of History, Stanford University
1975, August 18 Died, Palo Alto, California
Series Description
- Correspondence 1942-1951. (Box 1)
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
- Speeches and Writings 1929-1967. (Box 1)
  Drafts and printed copies of speeches and writings arranged alphabetically by title.
- Subject File 1920-1946. (Box 1-3)
  Biographical file, reports, research notes, newsletters, printed matter, lists, miscellany, arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Research Card Files 1875-1975. (Box 4-17)
  Notecards on various research interests, arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Audio-Visual (A-V)
  See photo card catalog.
- Medals
  See medal collection.
- Undescribed materials (Box 18)
- Writings, correspondence and clippings, 1926-1988 (Box 19-23)
  Relate to the Balkans during World War I, Otto von Bismarck, the Englightenment, and the Harris Fellowships in History at Stanford University
- Declassified records, 1948-1949 (Box 23)
  Formerly security-classified U.S. records. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1942-1951
  - Allen, Henry E., 1948 (Box 1.)
  - Allen, P. E., 1942
  - Beam, Jacob D., 1948
  - Bonbright, James C. H., 1947
  - Corrick (first name unknown), 1943
  - Eden, Anthony, 1943
  - Heath, Donald R., 1945, 1947
  - Hickerson, John (Department of State, Cental European Affairs), 1947-1951
  - Kindlebey, Charles P., n.d.
  - Kirk, Dudley, 1942
  - Lutz, Ralph, 1942
  - Martin, H. P., 1951
  - Mosely, Philip E., 1943-1945
  - Murphy, Robert (U.S. Political Advisor on German Affairs), 1946-1947
  - Nicholas, Harry I., Jr., n.d.
  - Noble, Bernard, 1950
  - Notter, Harley A., 1942-1943
  - Reker, Anna Mae, 1947
  - Riddleberger, Jimmie, 1947
  - Russell, Francis H., 1951
  - Shaw, G. Howland, 1944
  - Smyth, Howard, 1942-1946
  - Stettinius, Edward R., Jr. (Undersecretary, Department of State), 1944
  - Trivers, Howard, 1948-1951
  - Truman, Harry S., 1954
  - Winart, John G. (U.S. Ambassador to Great Britain), 1945-1946
  - Yardley, Edward, 1942
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1929-1967
  - "Diplomatic History of the Balkan Crisis of 1875-1878, The Second Year," a sequel to Diplomatic History of the Balkan Crisis of 1875-1878: The First Year. An unpublished, unfinished draft of Chapter I (typewritten), 1967 (Box 1.)
  - "Future of the Kellogg Pact." Speech (typewritten) given in South Carolina, 1929
  - "Key to What." Speech (typewritten) given before the Phi Beta Kappa, Stanford, 1962
  - "On History: Research and Writing." Unpublished article (typewritten), n.d.
  - "Reflections on the Last Great War and Next." Speech (typewritten) given in 1936
  - "Twenty-four Years After." Speech (typewritten) to the Kiwanis International, Chicago, 1938
  - Untitled speeches given at Yuba Junion College, 1935, at Chico, 1937
- SUBJECT FILE, 1920-1946
  - "Armistice or No Armistice: the Legal Aspect." Unpublished draft report (typewritten carbon copy), 1943 (Box 1.)
  - Austria, post World War II treatment
  - Balkan Crisis of 1875-1878, pamphlets
  - Biographical file
  - Council of Foreign Ministers
    - "Draft Statement for Submission to the Council of Foreign Ministers." Unpublished draft (typewritten carbon copy), 1946
    - United States policy during Council of Foreign Ministers Meeting, London. Unpublished report (handwritten), 1947
  - France
    - Saar discussions with the French. Unpublished draft report (handwritten), 1947
  - "French Peace Aimes," Dwight E. Lee, editor. Unpublished article (typewritten), 1943
  - Germany
    - Changes in governmental structure, n.d.
    - Disarmament and demilitarization, 1946
    - "Franco-German Armistice Convention of June 22, 1940." Unpublished draft report (typewritten carbon copy), n.d.
    - "Geographical Analysis of the Rectification of the German-Czech Border, suggested by Czechoslovakia." Research report prepared by Division of Map Intelligence and Cartography, 1946
    - "Implementation of the Potsdam Declaration: Democratization and Denazification." Report (typewritten) issued by the U.S. Department of State, 1947
    - Memorandum on the Dusseldorf Agreement. Memorandum (typewritten) issued by the U.S. Department of State, 1943
    - Partition, 1943-1944 (Box 2.)
    - Political/economic agricultural graphs, 1920-1939
    - Political parties, policies regarding foreign policy, 1920-1933
    - Post-war education, 1944
    - Procedures for peace settlement with Allies, 1947
    - Regional and local government, n.d.
    - Rhineland Separation, 1918-1945
    - "Surrender: With Whom to Deal." Incomplete unpublished draft (typewritten carbon copy), n.d.
    - Treatment of, 1942 (Box 3.)
    - United States Policy, 1945
    - Voting elections, 1924-1933
  - Jessup, Philip C., "The Nature and Consequences of Unconditional Surrender under International Law." Unpublished draft (typewritten carbon copy), 1944
  - Holland, Lord and Lady Charles
  - Miscellany
  - National Committee of Free Germany, 1943
  - Paris Peace Conference. "The Sudeten-German Problem at the Paris Peace Conference of 1919." Issued document (typewritten), 1942
  - Poland, American position on boundary, 1942
  - The Socialist Unity Party of Germany: Manifesto, n.d.
  - Tripartite Conference, 1943, 1945
  - United States, Office of Military Government, 1946
- RESEARCH CARD FILES, 1875-1975
  - Balkan Crisis of 1875-1878 (Box 4-13.)
  - Holland, Lord and Lady Charles, n.d. (Box 14.)
  - Napoleon, Emperor of France, 1804-1815 (Box 15-17.)
- Undescribed materials (Box 18)
- Writings, correspondence and clippings, 1926-1988 (Box 19-23)
- Declassified records, 1948-1949 (Box 23)
  - 2011 September release of records, 1948-1949 (Box 23)
    Correspondence with Howard Trivers, Department of State